Wittner, Lawrence; Papers apap100
M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections & Archives
Lawrence S. Wittner Papers
1977-2019
M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections & Archives
apap100
3.16 cubic ft.
The Lawrence S. Wittner Papers document Dr. Wittner's activism in politics and his work with United University Professions, the Albany County Central Federation of Labor, the Solidarity Committee of the Capital District, the Albany Chapter of Democratic Socialists of America, Upper Hudson Peace Action, and various other social justice and peace organizations in the Capital Region.
Access
Access to this record group is unrestricted.
Acquisition Information
Dr. Lawrence Wittner donated all of the materials in this collection to the M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections and Archives in 2000, 2011 and 2022.
Biographical Sketch
Dr. Lawrence S. Wittner joined the History Department at the University at Albany in 1974 and retired as Professor of History in 2010. He is currently Professor of History Emeritus. He has held various positions in the leadership of United University Professions, the Albany County Central Federation of Labor (ACCFL), the Solidarity Committee of the Capital District, the Capital District Chapter of the World Federalist Association, Democratic Socialists of America (DSA), and Upper Hudson Peace Action. In 1979 he was first elected a member of the Albany UUP Executive Committee, and he continued serving in this capacity until 2017, including four years (1983 to 1987) as Vice-President for Academics. He also chaired the statewide UUP Solidarity Committee and, since 1979, has been an Albany UUP delegate to the ACCFL, serving as ACCFL executive secretary from 2011 to 2016 and as a member of the ACCFL executive committee since 2011.
Dr. Wittner was one of the founders of Albany DSOC/DSA. From 1981 to 1984 he was secretary of the organization, serving as a DSA National Board delegate in 1983. He also co-chaired the Capital District Labor-Religion Coalition from 1982 to 1984 and served as vice president of the Capital District chapter of the World Federalist Association from 1990 to 1995.
Over the years, he was also active in local and national election campaigns, including the campaigns of Ed Bloch (1984 and 1986), Nancy Burton (1985), Michael Dukakis (1988), Leon Van Dyke (1989 and 1993), Doug Bullock (2015 and 2019), and Alfredo Balarin (2016 and 2020). In 2015-2016, he was a leader in the Bernie Sanders presidential campaign in New York's 20th congressional district, and the voters in the 2016 Democratic primary elected him as a Sanders delegate to the Democratic National Convention.
Dr. Wittner received his A.B. from Columbia College, his M.A. in History from the University of Wisconsin and his Ph.D. in History from Columbia University. He is the author of numerous books, articles, reviews, and other scholarly works, and is a recipient of many scholarly grants and awards. He served numerous terms on the board of the Peace History Society (an affiliate of the American Historical Association) from 1970 to 2007, including two years as president (1977-1979), as a board member of the Society for Historians of American Foreign Relations (1982-1984) and as chair of the Peace History Commission of the International Peace Research Association (1998-2001). He has delivered lectures in dozens of countries, including lectures at the Norwegian Nobel Institute and at the United Nations.
Scope and Contents
The Lawrence S. Wittner Papers consist of materials pertaining to Dr. Wittner's many years of political activism within the Capital Region as well as nationally and internationally. Folders in Series 2 and 3 contain many different political issues or events led or attended by Dr. Wittner. Series 1 consists of a large amount of correspondence, agendas, and flyers for Democratic Socialist Organizing Committee (DSOC) and Democratic Socialists of America (DSA).
Arrangement of the Collection
The collection is organized into the following series:
Series 1 - Democratic Socialist of America/Democratic Socialist Organizing Committee (DSA/SOC), 1980-1987, Undated
Series 2 - United University Professions (UUP) Solidarity Committee, 1986-2001, Undated
Series 3 - Other Activism, 1977-2007
Series 1 is arranged chronologically while Series 2 and 3 are arranged alphabetically.
Social Activists and Public Advocates; Labor; Albany, New York; Political activists--United States; Labor unions--United States; New York (State)--Politics and government; Articles; Correspondence; Memorandums; Wittner, Lawrence S.; University at Albany, State University of New York; United University Professions (Association: N.Y.); Democratic Socialists of America; Democratic Socialist Organizing Committee (U.S.)
- Democratic Socialist of America/Democratic Socialist Organizing Committee (DSA/SOC), 1980-1987; Undated; 1; 1.16 cubic ft.
  Arrangement
  Arranged chronologically.
  Scope and Contents
  The series includes meeting minutes, agendas, financial statements, flyers and correspondence referring to various projects in the Capital District. There are also some DSA subject files. In addition, the series includes issues of The Albany Anvil, the monthly newsletter of the organization. The newsletter was a project of the Social Justice Center that started almost immediately after the group formed in 1981. May 1981 to May 1996, December 1996 and May-June 1987 are available.
  - Miscellaneous Leaflets and Articles, 1978-1981; 1985; Undated (Box 1 (1-Democratic Socialist of America/Democratic Sociali), Folder 1)
  - DSOC Correspondence, Notes, and Flyers, 1980 December-1981 June (Box 1 (1-Democratic Socialist of America/Democratic Sociali), Folder 2)
  - DSA Constitution, By-Laws, Governance, 1980-1983 (Box 1 (1-Democratic Socialist of America/Democratic Sociali), Folder 3)
  - The Albany Anvil, 1981 May-1983 December (Box 1 (1-Democratic Socialist of America/Democratic Sociali), Folder 4)
  - DSOC Agendas, Correspondence, Notes, and Flyers, 1981 June-1981 December (Box 1 (1-Democratic Socialist of America/Democratic Sociali), Folder 5)
  - In These Times Promotion, 1981-1983 (Box 1 (1-Democratic Socialist of America/Democratic Sociali), Folder 6)
  - DSA National Board, 1981-1983 (Box 1 (1-Democratic Socialist of America/Democratic Sociali), Folder 7)
  - DSOC/DSA Agendas, Correspondence, Notes, and Flyers, 1982 January-1982 May (Box 1 (1-Democratic Socialist of America/Democratic Sociali), Folder 8)
  - DSA Agendas, Correspondence, News Releases Notes, and Flyers, 1982 June-1982 August (Box 2 (1-Democratic Socialist of America/Democratic Sociali), Folder 1)
  - DSA Agendas, Correspondence, News Releases Notes, and Flyers, 1982 September-1982 December (Box 2 (1-Democratic Socialist of America/Democratic Sociali), Folder 2)
  - Michael Harrington Visit, 1982 (Box 2 (1-Democratic Socialist of America/Democratic Sociali), Folder 3)
  - Mohasco Demonstration, 1982 (Box 2 (1-Democratic Socialist of America/Democratic Sociali), Folder 4)
  - John Dow Campaign, 1982 (Box 2 (1-Democratic Socialist of America/Democratic Sociali), Folder 5)
  - Debs Dinner, Invitations and Programs, 1982-1985; 1987 (Box 2 (1-Democratic Socialist of America/Democratic Sociali), Folder 6)
  - DSA Mailing Lists, 1982-1986; Undated (Box 2 (1-Democratic Socialist of America/Democratic Sociali), Folder 7)
  - DSA Agendas, Correspondence, News Releases Notes, and Flyers, 1983 January-1983 May (Box 2 (1-Democratic Socialist of America/Democratic Sociali), Folder 8)
  - DSA Agendas, Correspondence, News Releases, Notes, and Flyers, 1983 June-1983 December (Box 2 (1-Democratic Socialist of America/Democratic Sociali), Folder 9)
  - Gregg Bell Campaign, 1983 (Box 3 (1-Democratic Socialist of America/Democratic Sociali), Folder 1)
  - DSA National Convention, 1983 (Box 3 (1-Democratic Socialist of America/Democratic Sociali), Folder 2)
  - New York State DSA, 1983-1987 (Box 3 (1-Democratic Socialist of America/Democratic Sociali), Folder 3)
  - DSA Agendas, Correspondence, Notes, and Flyers, 1984 January-1984 June (Box 3 (1-Democratic Socialist of America/Democratic Sociali), Folder 4)
  - DSA Agendas, Correspondence, Notes, and Flyers, 1984 July-1984 December (Box 3 (1-Democratic Socialist of America/Democratic Sociali), Folder 5)
  - Barbara Ehrenreich Visit, 1984 (Box 3 (1-Democratic Socialist of America/Democratic Sociali), Folder 6)
  - Ads in Democratic Left, 1984 (Box 3 (1-Democratic Socialist of America/Democratic Sociali), Folder 7)
  - The Albany Anvil, 1984 January-1986 December (Box 3 (1-Democratic Socialist of America/Democratic Sociali), Folder 8)
  - Democratic Committee Races, 1984; 1986 (Box 3 (1-Democratic Socialist of America/Democratic Sociali), Folder 9)
  - DSA Agendas, Correspondence, Notes, and Flyers, 1985 January-1985 June (Box 3 (1-Democratic Socialist of America/Democratic Sociali), Folder 10)
  - DSA Agendas, Correspondence, Notes, and Flyers, 1985 July-1985 December (Box 4 (1-Democratic Socialist of America/Democratic Sociali), Folder 1)
  - Nancy Burton Campaign, 1985 (Box 4 (1-Democratic Socialist of America/Democratic Sociali), Folder 2)
  - Jeremy Karapatkin Visit, Student DSA, 1985 (Box 4 (1-Democratic Socialist of America/Democratic Sociali), Folder 3)
  - DSA Agendas, Correspondence, Notes, and Flyers, 1986 January-1986 October (Box 4 (1-Democratic Socialist of America/Democratic Sociali), Folder 4)
  - Democratic Alternatives Conference, 1987 (Box 4 (1-Democratic Socialist of America/Democratic Sociali), Folder 5)
  - Membership Survey, Undated (Box 4 (1-Democratic Socialist of America/Democratic Sociali), Folder 6)
- United University Professions (UUP) Solidarity Committee, 1986-2001; Undated; 2; 0.80 cubic ft.
  Arranged alphabetically.
  This series consists of administrative documents and paperwork such as agendas, minutes, correspondence and financial statements for the UUP's Solidarity Committee. It also consists of correspondence, clippings and general information about various issues being tackled by the group. The subject files include: Amalgamated Clothing and Textile Workers' Union, Brooklyn Union Gas Lockout, Cargill Salt Miners' Strike, Coors Boycott, CWA, Grape Boycott, Independent Federation of Flight Attendants, Labor Councils and other AFL-CIO Affiliations, Mexican Workers, National Association of Broadcast Employees and Technicians, New Labor Struggles, NYS Labor-Religion Coalition, NYS Nurses' Association, Nicaragua Labor Support, Onondaga Community College Federation of Teachers, Portec Strike, Publicity for Manny Fields' plays, Social Agenda, Solidarnosc, South Africa Fund, South Africa Labor Support, Support for Overseas Unions, Tugboat and Barge Workers, United Paperworkers International Union, and the Zinc Miners' Strike.
  - Amalgamated Clothing and Textile Workers Union (ACTWU) Local 1712, Strike in Gloversville, 1987-1988 (Box 1 (2-United University Professions (UUP) Solidarity Com), Folder 1)
  - Amalgamated Clothing and Textile Workers Union (ACTWU) Local 791, Strike in Hudson, 1987 (Box 1 (2-United University Professions (UUP) Solidarity Com), Folder 2)
  - Brooklyn Union Gas Lockout, Transportation Workers Union (TWU), 1986 (Box 1 (2-United University Professions (UUP) Solidarity Com), Folder 3)
  - Campaign for a Living Wage, Albany County, 1995-1998; Undated (Box 1 (2-United University Professions (UUP) Solidarity Com), Folder 4)
  - Cargill Salt Miners' Strike, International Association of Machinists (IAM) in Lansing, MI, 1986-1987 (Box 1 (2-United University Professions (UUP) Solidarity Com), Folder 5)
  - Communication Workers of America (CWA) Local 1168, Buffalo, 1987 (Box 1 (2-United University Professions (UUP) Solidarity Com), Folder 6)
  - Coors Boycott, 1987 (Box 1 (2-United University Professions (UUP) Solidarity Com), Folder 7)
  - Grape Boycott, United Farm Workers (UFW), 1987-1988 (Box 1 (2-United University Professions (UUP) Solidarity Com), Folder 8)
  - Independent Federation of Flight Attendants, 1987 (Box 1 (2-United University Professions (UUP) Solidarity Com), Folder 9)
  - Labor Committee for Peace and Justice in South America, 1988 (Box 1 (2-United University Professions (UUP) Solidarity Com), Folder 10)
  - Labor Councils and other AFL-CIO Affiliations, 1988 (Box 1 (2-United University Professions (UUP) Solidarity Com), Folder 11)
  - Mexican Unions, 1995 (Box 1 (2-United University Professions (UUP) Solidarity Com), Folder 12)
  - Minutes, Agendas, Correspondence, Financial Records, 1986-1987 (Box 1 (2-United University Professions (UUP) Solidarity Com), Folder 13)
  - Minutes, Agendas, Correspondence, Financial Records, 1987-1988 (Box 1 (2-United University Professions (UUP) Solidarity Com), Folder 14-15)
  - Minutes, Agendas, Correspondence, Financial Records, 1988-1989 (Box 1 (2-United University Professions (UUP) Solidarity Com), Folder 16)
  - Minutes, Agendas, Correspondence, Financial Records, 1989-1991 (Box 1 (2-United University Professions (UUP) Solidarity Com), Folder 17)
  - Minutes, Agendas, Correspondence, Financial Records, 1991-1992 (Box 1 (2-United University Professions (UUP) Solidarity Com), Folder 18)
  - Minutes, Agendas, Correspondence, Financial Records, 1992-1993 (Box 1 (2-United University Professions (UUP) Solidarity Com), Folder 19)
  - Minutes, Agendas, Correspondence, Financial Records, 1994-1995 (Box 1 (2-United University Professions (UUP) Solidarity Com), Folder 20)
  - Minutes, Agendas, Correspondence, Financial Records, 1995-1996 (Box 1 (2-United University Professions (UUP) Solidarity Com), Folder 21)
  - Minutes, Agendas, Correspondence, Financial Records, 1996-1997 (Box 1 (2-United University Professions (UUP) Solidarity Com), Folder 22)
  - Minutes, Agendas, Correspondence, Financial Records, 1997-1998 (Box 1 (2-United University Professions (UUP) Solidarity Com), Folder 23)
  - Minutes, Agendas, Correspondence, Financial Records, 1998-1999 (Box 1 (2-United University Professions (UUP) Solidarity Com), Folder 24)
  - Minutes, Agendas, Correspondence, Financial Records, 2000-2001 (Box 2 (2-United University Professions (UUP) Solidarity Com), Folder 1)
  - National Association of Broadcast Employees and Technicians (NABET), Local 21, Schenectady, 1987 (Box 2 (2-United University Professions (UUP) Solidarity Com), Folder 2)
  - New Labor Struggles, 1986-1987 (Box 2 (2-United University Professions (UUP) Solidarity Com), Folder 3)
  - New York State Labor-Religion Coalition, 1988 (Box 2 (2-United University Professions (UUP) Solidarity Com), Folder 4)
  - New York State Nurses Association, Malone, NY, 1988 (Box 2 (2-United University Professions (UUP) Solidarity Com), Folder 5)
  - Nicaragua Labor Support, 1988 (Box 2 (2-United University Professions (UUP) Solidarity Com), Folder 6)
  - Onondaga Community College Federation of Teachers, 1987 (Box 2 (2-United University Professions (UUP) Solidarity Com), Folder 7)
  - Portec Strike, United Steel Workers, 1986 (Box 2 (2-United University Professions (UUP) Solidarity Com), Folder 8)
  - Publicity for Manny Fried's Plays, 1988 (Box 2 (2-United University Professions (UUP) Solidarity Com), Folder 9)
  - Social Agenda, 1987-1988 (Box 2 (2-United University Professions (UUP) Solidarity Com), Folder 10)
  - Solidarnosc, 1988 (Box 2 (2-United University Professions (UUP) Solidarity Com), Folder 11)
  - South Africa Fund, 1988-1995 (Box 2 (2-United University Professions (UUP) Solidarity Com), Folder 12)
  - South Africa Labor Support, 1987-1992 (Box 2 (2-United University Professions (UUP) Solidarity Com), Folder 13)
  - Support for Overseas Unions, 1987-1988 (Box 2 (2-United University Professions (UUP) Solidarity Com), Folder 14)
  - Tugboat and Barge Workers, International Longshoremen's Association (ILA), 1988 (Box 2 (2-United University Professions (UUP) Solidarity Com), Folder 15)
  - United Paperworkers International Union (UPIU) Jay, ME Local 14, 1988 (Box 2 (2-United University Professions (UUP) Solidarity Com), Folder 16)
  - Zinc Miners' Strike, United Steelworkers, Gouverneur, NY, 1987 (Box 2 (2-United University Professions (UUP) Solidarity Com), Folder 17)
- Other Activism, 1977-2007; 3; 1.20 cubic ft.
  Dr. Wittner's activism included other organizations such as the Americans against Nuclear War, Capital District Anti-Nuclear Alliance, Capital District Labor-Religion Coalition and the World Federalist Association. In addition, this series includes Dr. Wittner's involvement in local political campaigns throughout the 1980s including those of Ed Bloch, Nancy Burton and Leon Van Dyke.
  - Albany Anti-War Actions, 2001 (Box 1 (3-Other Activism), Folder 1)
  - Albany Public School Teachers, 1987-1988 (Box 1 (3-Other Activism), Folder 2)
  - Albany UUP Chapter, 1978-1994 (Box 1 (3-Other Activism), Folder 3)
  - Americans Against Nuclear War, 1985 (Box 1 (3-Other Activism), Folder 4)
  - Anti-Apartheid Demonstration, 1984-1985 (Box 1 (3-Other Activism), Folder 5)
  - Art Rodriguez Tour, United Farm Workers (UFW), 1989 April 05-1989 April 06 (Box 1 (3-Other Activism), Folder 6)
  - Campus Action, 1993-1999 (Box 1 (3-Other Activism), Folder 7)
  - Capital District Anti-Nuclear Alliance, 1979-1982 (Box 1 (3-Other Activism), Folder 8)
  - Capital District Chapter of the Labor Party, 1994-1998 (Box 1 (3-Other Activism), Folder 9)
  - Capital District Labor-Religion Coalition, 1985 (Box 1 (3-Other Activism), Folder 10)
  - Capital Region Social Forum, 2004 (Box 1 (3-Other Activism), Folder 11)
  - Capital Region Social Forum, 2007 (Box 1 (3-Other Activism), Folder 12)
  - Cesar Chavez Appearance, 1987 April 02 (Box 1 (3-Other Activism), Folder 13)
  - Cornell Industrial and Labor Relations School, Classes Hosted at Hudson Valley Community College, 1983-1985 (Box 1 (3-Other Activism), Folder 14)
  - Dukakis Campaign, 1988 (Box 1 (3-Other Activism), Folder 15)
  - Ed Bloch Campaign, 1984-1986 (Box 1 (3-Other Activism), Folder 16)
  - Ed Bloch Campaign, 1984-1986 (Box 2 (3-Other Activism), Folder 1)
  - El Salvador Ad, National Labor Committee, 1982 March 28 (Box 2 (3-Other Activism), Folder 2)
  - Food Service Workers' Campaign, SUNY Albany, 1999-2001 (Box 2 (3-Other Activism), Folder 3-5)
  - Greyhound Strike, 1983 (Box 2 (3-Other Activism), Folder 6)
  - Hiroshima 60th Anniversary Events in Albany, 2005 (Box 2 (3-Other Activism), Folder 7)
  - In These Times Group, 1977-1978 (Box 2 (3-Other Activism), Folder 8)
  - James Bay Project, 1991 (Box 2 (3-Other Activism), Folder 9)
  - Leon Van Dyke Campaigns for Albany School Board and Alderman, 1989; 1993 (Box 2 (3-Other Activism), Folder 10)
  - May 1st Anti-Nuclear Weapon Demonstration, 2005 (Box 2 (3-Other Activism), Folder 11)
  - Mayors for Peace, 2005 (Box 2 (3-Other Activism), Folder 12)
  - Moral Majority, 1980 (Box 2 (3-Other Activism), Folder 13)
  - National Labor Committee, Protest of Clothing from Sweatshops, 1995-1999 (Box 2 (3-Other Activism), Folder 14)
  - New York State Coalition, Nancy Burton Campaign, 1985 (Box 3 (3-Other Activism), Folder 1)
  - Nicaragua Ad, NYS United Teachers, 1986 (Box 3 (3-Other Activism), Folder 2)
  - NL Industries, 1979 (Box 3 (3-Other Activism), Folder 3)
  - Nuclear Abolition Activities, 2005 (Box 3 (3-Other Activism), Folder 4)
  - Peace Action's Peace Voter Campaign, 2000 (Box 3 (3-Other Activism), Folder 5)
  - SUNY Peace and Justice, 2005-2006 (Box 3 (3-Other Activism), Folder 6)
  - SUNY Peace and Justice Group, Iraq War Talks, 2002-2003 (Box 3 (3-Other Activism), Folder 7)
  - Tax the Rich Program, 1989 (Box 3 (3-Other Activism), Folder 8)
  - Teach-In: A Labor Movement, 1997 (Box 3 (3-Other Activism), Folder 9-10)
  - Teach-In at the SUNY Albany Campus, 2002 (Box 3 (3-Other Activism), Folder 11)
  - UUP Contract Battle, 1985-1986 (Box 3 (3-Other Activism), Folder 12)
  - World Federalist Association, Capital District Chapter, 1988-1997 (Box 3 (3-Other Activism), Folder 13)